Preliminary Inventory of the Keith L. Nelson papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Keith L. Nelson papers
1919-1975
2008C15
Nelson, Keith L.
17 manuscript boxes (6.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, notes, photocopies of government and other documents, and printed matter, relating to the post-World War I Allied occupation of the Rhineland, especially by African colonial troops. Used as research material for the book by K. L. Nelson, Victors Divided: America and the Allies in Germany, 1918-1923 (Berkeley, 1975).
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to sound recordings, video recordings, or motion picture material requires at least two weeks advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2008.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
American historian, a Professor of History, former Director of the Center for Global Peace and Conflict Studies at the University of California, Irvine.
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, notes, photocopies of government and other documents, and printed matter, relating to the post-World War I Allied occupation of the Rhineland, especially by African colonial troops. Used as research material for the book by K. L. Nelson, Victors Divided: America and the Allies in Germany, 1918-1923 (Berkeley, 1975).
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Germany--History--Allied occupation, 1918-1930.
Collection Contents
- Microfilm reels
  - War Dept records (World War I Branch, War Records Division) in the National Archives. Record Group 94 (Adjutant General's Office). Record Group 120 (AEF) -Third Army file, AFG file (which includes a two volume typewritten "History of the American Forces Germany") (Box 1.)
  - Papers of Myron Herrick, American Ambassador to France, from the Western Reserve Historical Society, Cleveland (Box 1.)
  - Papers of Bernard Baruch and Ray Stannard Baker from the Princeton University Library (Box 1.)
  - sections of the Koblenzstaatsarchiv card catalogue -Edward Beerbusse dissertation ("Diplomatic Relations between the US and Weimar Germany,1919-1929") Joseph Aulneau writing (Le Rhin et la France, 1921) (Box 1.)
  - Materials from the Koblenzstaatsarchiv Abteilung 403, records of the Oberpräsident der Rheinprovinz (Box 1.)
  - Bibliothèque de Documentation Internationale Contemporaine (Paris) relevant card catalogue entries and records of the censorship service [see "Guide" folder, below], (2 reels) (Box 1.)
  - Diary Marshall Ferdinand Foch (Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris) (Box 1.)
  - Papers of General Charles Mangin, Archives Nationales, Paris [see "Guide" folder, below], (2 reels) (Box 1.)
  - Papers of P. Forthomme, Paul Hymans, Edouard Rolin-Jacquemyns from the Archives Générales du Royaume in Brussels [see "Guide" folder, below] (Box 1.)
- Files
  - Black Troops material I (contemporary books, pamphlets, articles, flyers) (Box 1.)
  - Black Troops material II (contemporary books, pamphlets, articles, flyers) (Box 1.)
  - Victors Divided Bibliography (Box 2-4.)
  - Keith L. Nelson Vita (Box 2-4.)
  - Pierrepont Noyes Unpublished Diary (American Rhineland Commissioner,1919-1920) - 202 pages (uncorrected and corrected versions) Includes letter he wrote subsequently about his visit in 1924 with former President Wilson (Box 2-4.)
  - Notes taken by Keith Nelson in 1965 at the Bibliothèque de Service Historique in Vincennes, the Archives Archives Générales du Royaume in Brussels, and during his interviews with Lord Kilmarnock and Lord Robertson, (2 binders) (Box 2-4.)
- Microfilm Reels (Box 2-4.)
  - State Dept records in the National Archives (1917-1923) Record Group 59 862t.01/8-1055, Record Group 256 purport sheets for 185.1711, documents from 181.228/2-74A, 181.31/28,184.013102/50, 185.121/12-20 (Box 2-4.)
  - State Dept records in the National Archives (1917-1923) Record Group 59 462.00 R 29, 294, 296, 711.62119, 763.72119, 862.00/99, Record Group 84 -- Coblenz Post, Record Group 256 181.22401,185.001/48, 185.1711 (Box 2-4.)
  - Relevant records in the Library of Congress (Chandler Anderson, Leland Harrison, Paul H. Clark, William Borah, Woodrow Wilson) (Box 2-4.)
  - Records of the Inquiry relevant to Germany, France, Belgium (14 frames) from the Columbia University Library (Box 2-4.)
  - British Foreign Ministry documents in Lord Curzon Papers, Derby, England (174 exposures), Correspondence with Derby, 1919-1920, Correspondence with Sir A Geddes, 1920-1921, Memo on Productive Pledges 1923, German Separatism 1924 [see "Guide" folder, below] (Box 2-4.)
  - British Foreign Ministry documents in Lord Curzon Papers, Derby, England (1666 exposures) Germany 1921-1924, Proposed Anglo-Belgian Pact 1919-1922, Imperial Conferences 1919-1922, Correspondence with Graham, Kerr, Kilmarnock, 1920, Correspondence with Hardinge, Crewe, Baldwin, and Poincaré 1920-1924 [see "Guide" folder, below] (Box 2-4.)
  - Papers relating to an Anglo-French Pact (46 exposures) (Box 2-4.)
  - Records of German Foreign Ministry, available from the National Archives (US), Records for the Period before 1920, Political Department, 1867-1920, File established during the Weimar National Assembly, German Peace Delegation File Records for the Period After 1920, Office of the Reichsminister (Foreign Minister), Office of the Staatssekretär (Box 2-4.)
  - Relevant records of the German Embassy at Washington (1921-1930), available from the National Archives (US) (Box 2-4.)
  - Materials from the Deutsches Zentral Archiv, Potsdam Waffenstillstandskommission Reichskommissar für die besetzten rheinischen Gebiete, Reichsministerium für die besetzten Gebiete, (2 reels - Auftrag 01163, in metal can) (Box 2-4.)
  - Erich Koch-Weser papers [Aktenstücke 13,14 (reel I), 22,23 (reel II), 27-29 (reel III), and 78, 82-84 (reel IV)] from the Koblenzstaatsarchiv censorship service [see "Guide" folder, below], (4 metal reels) (Box 2-4.)
  - Le Matin (October 25 -November 25, 1921) (Box 2-4.)
- PhD dissertations on Microfilm Reels (Box 2-4.)
  - J. H. Mannock, "Anglo-American Relations, 1921-1928" (Princeton, 1962) (Box 2-4.)
  - Barbara Ann Welter, "The US and Weimar Germany" (Wisconsin, 1960) (Box 2-4.)
  - D. S. Birn, "Britain and Germany at the Washington Conference, 1921-1922" (Columbia, 1965) (Box 2-4.)
  - W. R. Schilling, "Admirals and Foreign Policy" (Box 2-4.)
  - J. M. Helmreich, "Belgian Diplomatic Style" (Princeton, 1961) (Box 2-4.)
  - D. S. White, "Franco-American Relations in 1917-1918" (Penn, 1954) (Box 2-4.)
  - R. E. Cleveland, "French Attitudes toward the German Problem 1914-1919" (Nebraska, 1956) (Box 2-4.)
  - Frances B. Lowry, "The Generals, the Armistice, and the Treaty of Versailles" (Duke, 1963) (Box 2-4.)
  - Raynsford, MA thesis on Pierrepont Noyes (Box 2-4.)
- Correspondence relating to the Dissertation and Book (Box 5-7.)
- Guides: Henry T. Allen, Registry of his papers in the Library of Congress Preliminary Inventory 89, Introduction (8 pages) to Records of the American Commission to Negotiate Peace (Washington 1955), Guide to the Papers of Paul Hymans (Brussels) on microfilm reel above, Guide to the BDIC archives (Paris) on microfilm reel above, Index to the Mangin papers (Paris) on microfilm reels above, List to the holdings of the HCITR in the Archives Nationales (Paris) (Box 5-7.)
- Indexes prepared by Keith Nelson to the Curzon manuscripts and to the German records in the microfilm reels above (Box 5-7.)
- Articles on other military occupations (Box 5-7.)
- Information on the press, political parties, and leaders (US & foreign) (Box 5-7.)
- Letters from Wallace Day (American Deputy Rhineland Commissioner) to Keith Nelson (1961-1975) (Box 5-7.)
- Letters of Wallace Day to Keith Nelson (1961-1975) and interviews with Wallace Day (Box 5-7.)
- Personal possessions of Wallace H. Day (1919-1920) (Box 5-7.)
- Black Book -- recommendations from the Inquiry to the President (January 1919) and Notes on German Counter-proposals (June 1919) from the Woodrow Wilson Papers (Box 5-7.)
- Materials from the Frank Lowden Papers, University of Chicago Library (Box 5-7.)
- Letters of Malcolm Robertson (British Commissioner) to his wife, 1919-1921, and excerpts from his unpublished autobiography-- Letters in the papers of Baron Edouard Rolin-Jacquemyns and P. Forthomme (Belgian representatives in the Rhineland), 1921-1925 (Box 5-7.)
- Photocopied pages from the reels of the Marshal Ferdinand Foch Diary, 1918-1922 (see above), (5 folders and one yellow box) (Box 5-7.)
- Relevant passages from Georges Clemenceau's Memoirs (Box 5-7.)
- Paul Tirard, Rapport sur l'administration des territories occupés (11 novembre 1918-28 juin 1919), pp 26-30, 52-55 (Box 5-7.)
- Minutes of the first three meetings of the IRHC (1920) Official Gazette of the IRHC, including Ordonnance #1 (January 1920), Recueil des Ordonnances (ordinances grouped by subject) (1920-1921) (Box 5-7.)
- Index to Documents Diplomatiques: Conférence de Washington, 1921-1922 (Paris, 1923) (Box 5-7.)
- Tables des Notes Documentaires et Etudes (index of French white papers on the World War I period published from 1 Jan 1945 to Dec 31, 1947) (Paris 1948) (Box 5-7.)
- Relevant passages from Italian Prime Minister Sydney Sonnino's memoirs, with English translation (Box 5-7.)
- Newspaper clippings from the US press (1918-1923) (Box 5-7.)
- Words and music of Allied World War I songs relating to Germany and the Rhineland (Box 5-7.)
- Folders of Belgian, German, and British Documents (Box 8-10.)
  - Materials from Documents Diplomatiques Belges, 1920-1940; I (1920-1924) Bruxelles, 1964 (Box 8-10.)
  - German Foreign Ministry WK 30 (taken from reel 4080) January - February 1919 (Box 8-10.)
  - Akten der Reichskanzlei; Weimarer Republic, Kabinett Scheidemann (13 Feb - 20 June 1919) (Box 8-10.)
  - Akten der Reichskanzlei; Weimarer Republic, Kabinett Müller I (27 Mar 1920 - 21 Jun 1920) (Box 8-10.)
  - Akten der Reichskanzlei; Weimarer Republic, Kabinett Fehrenbach (25 Jun 1920 - 4 May 1921) (Box 8-10.)
  - Akten der Reichskanzlei; Weimarer Republic, Kabinett Cuno (22 Nov 1922-12 Aug 1923) (Box 8-10.)
  - British Wartime Documents (1916-1917), includes Overview of British Cabinet Records, Plan of the CAB 23 series, and notes from AJP Taylor, Politics in Wartime (Box 8-10.)
  - British War Cabinet - documents drawn from CAB 23/3-9 (July 1917-June 1919) (Box 8-10.)
  - British War Cabinet, Series A - documents drawn from CAB 23/14-15 (Oct 1918-March 1919) (Box 8-10.)
  - British Imperial War Cabinet - documents drawn from CAB 23/40-42 (March 1917-Dec 1918) (Box 8-10.)
  - British Cabinet - indexes to the Conclusions of Cabinet, Conference of Ministers, Home Affairs Committee, and Finance Committee (November 1919 - Dec 1921, Jan - Oct 1922), and Cabinet Minutes of 22 December 1921 (Box 8-10.)
  - British Foreign Office - Index the General Correspondence, 1920-1923, and K. Nelson correspondence with PRO (Box 8-10.)
  - British Foreign Office - Index to Confidential Print: Germany (FO 408) (Box 8-10.)
  - Records of the War Cabinet 23/35 - Conference of (International) Ministers (Dec 1919-Aug 1922) (Box 8-10.)
  - British Foreign Office Documents - FO 371/4598, 4807, 4742, 5881, 5989, 6064, 5857, 5973, 5974, 6073,5865, 7520, 7521, 7490, 7528, 8704 -- Comments on American Occupation, French troops, British policy, conditions in Rhineland, etc. (Feb 1920-Nov 1921), Confidential Print: Germany - FO 408/7-9 Comments on American Policies (Jan 1922-Feb 1923) (Box 8-10.)
  - British Foreign Office Documents, FO 371/5882-5883, Replacement of the Reichskommisar (May-June 1921) (Box 8-10.)
  - British Foreign Office Documents - FO 371/ 7544, 4730, 5989, 7548, 7549, 8678, Correspondence on US Army Costs 1921-1923, Confidential Print: Germany - FO 408/3-7, Army Costs January 1921-November 1922 (Box 8-10.)
  - British Foreign Office Documents - FO 371/ 4738, 4805, 4860, 4807, 4805, 6028, 5971, 6980, 5972, 5883, 6038; FO 395/362, British Correspondence between Coblenz & London (Jul 1920-Nov 1921) Confidential Print: Germany - FO 408/1, 7-8, Frankfurt Occupation, March 1920, French Move on Ruhr, April-December 1922 (Box 8-10.)
  - British Foreign Office Documents - FO 371/6016, 6024, Customs Frontier (March 1921), Meeting with Briand (April 1921), Confidential Print: Germany - FO 408/3-8, Sanctions & Licensing Organizations (Feb 1921-July 1922) (Box 8-10.)
  - British Foreign Office Documents - FO 371/6041, Belgian Attitudes (Feb-March 1921), Confidential Print: Germany - FO 408/8, Belgian Attitudes (November 1922) (Box 8-10.)
  - British Foreign Office Documents - FO 371/ 2703, 7521, 7523, 7537, 7581, 8680, 8690, 8708 - British policies in the Rhineland (May 1922-April 1923), with documents from 1918, 1919, & 1920 (Box 8-10.)
  - British Foreign Office Documents - FO 3714798, 4789, 4830, 4805, 5999, 6028, 5973 - material on the "Black Horror" (July 1920-January 1922) (Box 8-10.)
  - British Foreign Office Documents - FO 371/8749-50 British Attitudes toward "productive pledges" (Oct-Nov 1923) (Box 8-10.)
  - British Foreign Office Documents, Confidential Print: Germany - FO 408/9, Question of British Withdrawal (Jan-Feb 1923) (Box 8-10.)
  - British Foreign Office Documents - FO 371/12130/ 2-56, Kilmarnock to Austen Chamberlain, 31 December 1926, with Annual Report of IARHC for 1923 (Box 8-10.)
  - Kilmarnock Reports of 8 September 1922 and 31 July 1923 from Curzon Mss - includes London Observer 24 June 1923, pp 13-14 (Box 8-10.)
  - Published British Documents, Tripartite Agreement on Rhineland Occupation - June 1919, Tripartite Pact (France, Britain, US)- June 1919, Dawes Plan - August 30, 1924 (Box 8-10.)
- Research Files. Folders of relevant pages from Books and Articles (Box 11-12.)
  - Allen, Henry T., reviews of his Rhineland Journal (Box 11-12.)
  - Benoist, Charles, Souvenirs(Paris, 1934) (Box 11-12.)
  - Berger, Marcel and Paul Allard, Les Secrets de la Censure (Paris, 1932) (Box 11-12.)
  - Beyerhaus, G., Die Europa Politik des Marschalls Foch (Leipzig, 1942) (Box 11-12.)
  - Bouriard, Capitan, La Campagne Allemande contre les troupes noires (Paris 1922) from the Ministry of Defence Library, Old War Office Building, London (Box 11-12.)
  - Brecht, Arnold, The Political Education of Arnold Brecht (Princeton, 1970) (Box 11-12.)
  - Cambon, Henri, Paul Cambon: Correspondance (1940-1946) (Box 11-12.)
  - Chastenet, Jacques, Les Années d'Illusions, 1918-1931 (Paris, 1960) (Box 11-12.)
  - Cox, Frederick J., "The French Peace Plans" in edited volume (NY, 1956) (Box 11-12.)
  - Davis, Shelby, The French War Machine (London, Allen & Unwin, 1937), chapter 7 ("Coloured Troops") and chapter 8 ("The Colonial Army") (Box 11-12.)
  - Davis, Shelby "Reservoirs of Men", Thesis University of Geneva, 1934 (205 pages) (Box 11-12.)
  - Elben, Wolfgang, Das Problem der Kontinuität in der deutschen Revolution (1965) (Box 11-12.)
  - Elcock, Howard, Portrait of a Decision (London, 1972) (Box 11-12.)
  - Favez, Jean Claude, Le Reich devant l'occupation (Geneva, 1969) (Box 11-12.)
  - Fayolle, Emil, Cahiers secrets (Paris, 1964) (Box 11-12.)
  - Franck, Harry A., "Through Germany on Foot: II, Coblenz" (Harper's, August 1919)" (Box 11-12.)
  - Freidel, Frank, Over There (1964) (Box 11-12.)
  - Friedensburg, Ferdinand, "Die geheimne Abmachung" (1938) (Box 11-12.)
  - Gärtner, Margarete, Botschafterin des guten Willens (Bonn, 1955) (Box 11-12.)
  - Gignoux, C. J., L'Economie française (Paris, 1942) (Box 11-12.)
  - Groener, Wilhelm, Lebenserinnerungen (Göttingen, 1957) (Box 11-12.)
  - Hankey, Lord, The Supreme Control at the Paris Peace Conference (London, 1963) (Box 11-12.)
  - Heyland, Karl, Die Lehre von der Rheinlandbesetzung (Box 11-12.)
  - Hughes, Charles E., Autobiographical Notes (1973) (Box 11-12.)
  - Izoulet, Jean, Et pas de France sans Rhénanie (Paris, 1920) (Box 11-12.)
  - Jones - Whitehall Diary, I. 1916-1925 (London, 1969) (Box 11-12.)
  - Jones, K Paul, unpublished articles on Houghton and the Ruhr Reparations Crisis (Box 11-12.)
  - Lersner, Freiherr von, Versailles! (Berlin, 1921) (Box 11-12.)
  - Loucheur, Louis, Carnets secrets, 1908-1932 (Bruxelles, 1962) (Box 11-12.)
  - Mangin, Louis E., La France et le Rhin (Geneva, 1945) (Box 11-12.)
  - Marston, F. S., The Peace Conference of 1919 (London, 1944) (Box 11-12.)
  - Memoirs - Headlam-Morley, Hankey, Frances Stevenson, Maie Casey (Box 11-12.)
  - Miquel, Pierre, La Paix de Versailles (Paris, 1972) (Box 11-12.)
  - Miquel, Pierre, Poincaré (Paris, 1961) (Box 11-12.)
  - Morsey, Rudolf, Deutsche Zentrumspartei (1966) (Box 11-12.)
  - Nobecourt, Jacques, Une Histoire Politique de l'Armée (Paris, 1967) (Box 11-12.)
  - Obituaries (Box 11-12.)
  - Persil, Raoul, Mitterrand (Paris, 1949) (Box 11-12.)
  - Pinon, René, Le Redressement de la politique eu France, 1922 (Paris, 1923) (Box 11-12.)
  - Prunet, Denis, Le Maréchal Foch (1951) (Box 11-12.)
  - Richter, Johannes, Die Reichszentrale für Heimatdienst (Berlin, 1963) (Box 11-12.)
  - Roskill, Stephen, Naval Policy between the Wars (Box 11-12.)
  - Rothwel, V. H., British War Aims (Oxford, 1971) (Box 11-12.)
  - Saint-Aulaire, Auguste, Confession (Paris, 1953) (Box 11-12.)
  - Stone, Ralph A., Irreconcilables (1970) (Box 11-12.)
  - Suarez, Georges, Récit Historique de R. Poincaré (Paris, 1932) (Box 11-12.)
  - Trask, David, General Tasker Bliss (Philadelphia, 1966) (Box 11-12.)
  - Troughton, Ernest, It's Happening Again (London, 1944) (Box 11-12.)
  - Watson, David, Clémenceau (London, 1974) (Box 11-12.)
  - Weygand, Maxine, Mémoires (Paris, 1953-1957) (Box 11-12.)
  - Wolfe, Martin, The French Franc between Wars (NY, 1951) (Box 11-12.)
  - Wormser, Georges, La République de Clémenceau (Paris, 1961) (Box 11-12.)
- American and British Articles on the Ruhr Crisis (1923) (Box 13-17.)
- Articles relevant to the Rhineland in European journals (Box 13-17.)
- Articles relevant to the Rhineland in US journals (Box 13-17.)
- Mein Rheinland Tagebuch (Berlin, 1923). German translation of My Rhineland Journal by General Henry T. Allen (Box 13-17.)
- Two maps of American zone - used in Victors Divided (Box 13-17.)
- Detailed notes on documents and secondary sources surveyed organized by the type of document (Box 13-17.)
  - FRUS - PPC = notes taken on the State Department's published volumes on the Paris Peace Conference (PPC) and FRUS 1920, 1921, 1922, and 1923 (Box 13-17.)
  - State Decimal = notes taken on materials in the State Department's decimal files (Box 13-17.)
  - MSS = notes taken on materials in private manuscript collections (Box 13-17.)
  - Congress = notes taken on the Congressional record (1918-1923) (Box 13-17.)
  - NYT = notes taken on editorials and articles in the New York Times (1918-1923) (Box 13-17.)
  - Newspapers = notes taken on US newspapers other than the New York Times (1918-1923) (Box 13-17.)
  - Journals = note taken on articles in American magazines and popular journals (1918-1923) (Box 13-17.)
  - European Situation = notes taken on books and articles that analyze the post-war European situation (Box 13-17.)
  - Black Troops = notes taken on materials relating to the French use of Black troops in the Rhineland (Box 13-17.)
  - British Documents = notes taken on British governmental documents (Box 13-17.)
  - German policy and Opinion = notes taken on materials that focus on the postwar German mentality and situation (Box 13-17.)
  - German Documents = notes taken on German governmental documents (Box 13-17.)
  - American Army in Peacetime Occupation = notes taken on materials relating to the US military occupation in Germany 1918-1923 (Box 13-17.)
- Detailed notes on documents and secondary sources surveyed grouped by the way in which important parts of them relate to the chapters of the book Victors Divided (Box 13-17.)
  - Armistice and Occupation (1917-1918) (Box 13-17.)
  - Americans, French, and Rhinelanders (1918-1919) (Box 13-17.)
  - Unoccupied Germany (1918-1919) (Box 13-17.)
  - Paris Peace Conference (1919) (Box 13-17.)
  - Rhineland Commission/Rhineland Agreement (1919) (Box 13-17.)
  - Noyes and Participation (1919-1920) (Box 13-17.)
  - Solemn Referendum and Harding (1920-1921) (Box 13-17.)
  - Allen's Restraining Force (1920-1922) (Box 13-17.)
  - The Last Phase (1923-1924) (Box 13-17.)